DANIELA MASSICETI

21 Station Road Cambridge, CB1 2FB, UK Senior Researcher (Machine Learning)
Microsoft Research Cambridge

daniela.massiceti@gmail.com https://danielamassiceti.github.io

SUMMARY

I am a multi-disciplinary machine learning (ML) researcher working on "teachable AI" - sytems that can learn on-the-fly from small amounts of noisy, real-world data provided by an end-user. I hold a Ph.D in computer vision, a M.Sc in Neuroscience, and a B.Sc in Electrical & Computer Engineering. My core interests lie in developing ML models that drive interactive, teachable experiences across a range of domains - from accessibility to mixed reality. Some examples include i) my current work on teachable object recognisers for people who are blind, ii) my PhD work on chat bots that can answer questions about an image, and iii) my MSc work on navigation in virtual reality environments using spatial sound. My full research portfolio can be found here. I value working with a multi-disciplinary team, and am dedicated to doing research with real-world impact.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Researcher. Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Apr 2021-present

- Teachable AI Experiences (TaiX) team in the Future of Work theme. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE
- Open-sourced the ORBIT dataset and ORBIT Teachable Object Recognition benchmark on GitHub
- Machine learning lead in the winning team of the global internal Microsoft Hackathon (Oct 2021)
- Recipient of the Innovating for the Future Award at the Microsoft Ability Summit (May 2022)

Postdoctoral Research Fellow. St Edmund's College, Cambridge

Apr 2020-present

- 3-year non-stipendiary research fellowship

Researcher. Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Feb 2020-Mar 2021

- Project Tokyo team in the Future of Work theme. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE

EDUCATION & SELECTED AWARDS

D.Phil Engineering - Machine Learning (awarded with no corrections), University of Oxford

2015-2019

- Thesis: "Computer Vision & Natural Language Processing for People with Vision Impairment"
- Supervisors: Prof. Philip H.S. Torr, Dr Stephen Hicks. Examiners: Prof. Andrew Zisserman, Prof. Kristen Grauman.
- Bronze Engineering Award at *STEM4Britain* (awarded by UK Parliament House of Commons)

2018

- Winner of University of Oxford Tri-Innovate Competition (start-up pitch competition)

2017

M.Sc Neuroscience (with distinction), University of Oxford

2014-2015

- With Prof. Rafal Bogacz "Modelling Parkinson's Disease tremor with networks of weakly-coupled oscillators"
- With Dr Stephen Hicks "Sonic Vision: 3D visual-to-audio mappings for non-sighted navigation"

B.Sc Engineering - Electrical & Computer (cum laude), University of Cape Town

2010-2014

- With Prof. Fred Nicolls "Occluded body pose estimation and reconstruction of bed-bound patients for hospital monitoring"
- Best final year thesis (Siemens Prize) and finalist in SAIEE National Student Project Competition (2013)
- Top final year B.Sc Engineering gradudate (Engineering Council of South Africa medal; 2013)
- Top 4^{th} , 3^{rd} & 2^{nd} year student in Engineering faculty (2013, 2012, 2011)
- Top 4th, 3rd & 2nd year student in B.Sc Electrical & Computer Engineering (2013, 2012, 2011)
- UCT Engineering Faculty Dean's Merit List ($\geq 75\%$ average) (2010-2013)
- Golden Key International Honours Society (top academic 15% at UCT) (2010–2013)

National Senior Certificate (IEB South Africa), Holy Rosary School, Johannesburg

1996-2009

- Within Independent Examinations Board Top 50 Matriculants (top 5% in ≥ 6 subjects across South Africa) (2009)
- Deputy Head Girl and Dux Scholar at Holy Rosary School (2009)
- Holy Rosary School Honours (all-round academic, sporting and cultural excellence) (2009)

INTERNSHIP/CONSULTANCY POSITIONS

Machine Learning Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

June-Dec 2019

- Developed machine learning models which learn to recognise objects after only seeing a few examples (few-shot recognition)
- Contact: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE cecilym@microsoft.com

Machine Learning Intern, OxSight Ltd

Nov 2018

- Developed a machine learning model for predicting which images regions are salient for OxSight's smart-spectacles
- Contact: Dr Stephen Hicks stephen.hicks@oxsight.co.uk

Machine Learning Consultant, London Vision Clinic

May-July 2018

- Consulted on machine learning methods for automatic keratoconus prediction from retinal scans
- Contact: Dr Dan Reinstein dzr@londonvisionclinic.com

Visiting Student, Computer Vision Lab Dresden (CVLD), Technische Universität Dresden

Apr 2015

- Compared methods for image-based camera relocalisation using random forests and neural networks
- The project resulted in a paper which was accepted and published in ICRA 2017
- Contact: Prof Carsten Rother carsten.rother@iwr.uni-heidelberg.de

RESEARCH

Selected Publications. See Google Scholar for full list

- 1. Bronskill, J.*, Massiceti, D.*, Patacchiola, M.*, Hofmann, K., Nowozin, S., Turner, R.E., 2021. *Memory Efficient Meta-Learning with Large Images*. In 2021 Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS).
- Massiceti, D., Zintgraf, L., Bronskill, J., Theodorou, L., Harris, M.T., Cutrell, E., Morrison, C., Hofmann, K. and Stumpf, S., 2021. ORBIT: A Real-World Few-Shot Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV).
- 3. Theodorou, L., Massiceti, D., Zintgraf, L., Stumpf, S., Morrison, C., Cutrell, E., Harris, M. T. and Hofmann, K, 2021. Disability-first Dataset Creation: Lessons from Constructing a Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition with Blind and Low Vision Data Collectors. In 2021 ACM Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS).
- Grayson, M., Thieme, A., Marques, R., Massiceti, D., Cutrell, E., Morrison, C., 2020. A Dynamic AI System for Extending the Capabilities of Blind People. In Extended Abstracts of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA).
- 5. Massiceti, D.*, Dokania, P.K.*, Siddharth, N.* and Torr, P.H.S., 2018. Visual Dialogue without Vision or Dialogue. In 2018 Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) [Critiquing & Correcting Trends in ML Workshop].
- Massiceti, D., Siddharth, N., Dokania, P.K. and Torr, P.H.S., 2018. FlipDial: A Generative Model for Two-Way Visual Dialogue. In IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR). [accepted as oral]
- Massiceti, D., Hicks, S.L. and van Rheede, J.J., 2018. Stereosonic Vision: exploring visual-to-auditory sensory substitution mappings in an immersive virtual reality navigation paradigm. PLOS ONE 13(7): e0199389.
- 8. Hou, Q*, Massiceti, D.*, Dokania, P.K., Wei, Y., Cheng, M.M. and Torr, P.H.S., 2017. *Bottom-up top-down cues for weakly-supervised semantic segmentation*. In 2017 International Conference on Energy Minimization Methods in Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (EMMCVPR).
- 9. Massiceti, D., Krull, A., Brachmann, E., Rother, C. and Torr, P.H.S., 2017. *Random forests versus Neural Networks What's best for camera localization?*. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA).

Patents

- On an innovation in few-shot learning applied to avatar personalisation [under submission, commercially sensitive]

Selected Presentations

- Panel Discussion, Pursuing a Resilient and Sustainable Global Society Microsoft Research 30th Anniversary Panel Series
 on Generations of Inspirational and Impactful Research

 Dec 2021
- Sponsor Talk, Advancing Real-world Few-shot Learning with the ORBIT Dataset WiML workshop, NeurIPS Dec 2021
- Invited Talk, Using Few-shot Learning to Realize Teachable AI Systems Microsoft Research Summit Oct 2021

 Invited Talk, A Real-World Few-Shot Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition - VizWiz workshop, CVI Guest Lecture, An Introduction to Dataset Bias - Department of Computer Science, University of Camb 	
- Guest Lecture, An Introduction to Dataset Bias - Department of Computer Science, University of Cambon - Student Talk, A Generative Model for Visual Dialogue - OxBridge Women in Computer Science Conference of Computer Science of Computer Science Conference of Computer Science Conference of Computer Science of	
- Invited Talk, Teaching Computers to Chat - ATOM Science Society	Aug 2017
SELECTED SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS	11wg 2011
	2010 2010
- Pembroke College Senior Common Room (SCR) Senior Scholarship	2018-2019
- Facebook AI Research ParlAI Grant	2017-2019
- Skye Foundation Scholarship, and University of Oxford Engineering Science Departmental Scholarship	2015-2019
- Clarendon Fund Scholarship University of Cana Town Engineering Faculty Scholarship	2014-2015 2011-2013
 University of Cape Town Engineering Faculty Scholarship Klaus-Jurgen Bathe Scholarship 	2011-2013
 Klaus-Jurgen Bathe Scholarship University of Cape Town Engineering Faculty Entrance Scholarship, and Harry Allschwang Grant 	2012-2013
LEADERSHIP	
Organising committee member of the VizWiz workshop	2022-present
 VizWiz is an annual workshop at CVPR on computer vision research/technologies for the blind/low-vision 	n community
- I launched the ORBIT Few-Shot Object Recognition Challenge in 2022, a new ML competition at the wo	orkshop
Organising committee member of the Deep Learning Indaba	2017-present
- The Indaba is a globally-recognised community for African inclusion in machine learning and artificial integrated in the community of the co	telligence
- I co-organised the Indaba machine learning summer school in 2018 & 2019	
- I co-founded & lead the Mentorship Programme in 2020 & 2021, facilitating 200+ mentorship sessions for A	frican students
Industry officer of University of Oxford Women in Computer Science	2018 - 2019
- I engaged with society's industry partners (including Google, DeepMind, Facebook, Bloomberg, Microsof	t, and others)
 I coordinated termly office visits, technical talks, and coding and interview preparation workshops 	
Committee member of University of Oxford Women in Engineering	2016 - 2019
 I coordinated the 1st Women in Engineering Research Symposium, May 2018 	
President of Middle Common Room (MCR), Pembroke College	2017
- I was elected to represent the Pembroke College graduate body (350 members) in the College's Governing B	ody Committee
 I introduced per-student subsidies for welfare support, extra-curricular and academic activity 	
Treasurer and vice president of Middle Common Room (MCR), Pembroke College	2015-2017
- I managed an annual cash flow of £40,000-£50,000, and acquired £4000+ funding for academic and cultured £4000+ funding	ral events
 I was a member of Pembroke College Finance & Planning Committee and Student Development Commit 	tee
EXTRA-CURRICULAR	
Entrepreneurship	
- I began a web-design company for business/personal website development	2013-present
- I won a start-up competition at University of Oxford with an assistive tool idea for visually-impaired peo	ple 2017
Sporting	0016 0010
 I was on the University of Oxford 2nd swimming team Outreach 	2016-2018
- I mentored 1 student in the Oxford Engineering, Science and Technology (OxFEST) Mentorship Scheme	2018-2019
- I mentored 4 students in the Pembroke MCR/JCR Mentorship Scheme	2016-2018
- I volunteered 100+ hours at local orphanages, HIV/Aids homes and hospitals	2009-2013
- I tutored a class of high-school students from a rural South African school in Mathematics, Biology and I	Physics 2013
REFERENCES	